本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
Looks like your eyesight has returned.
視力も戻ったようですね
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
I can't believe the Church
would use you like that.
そこまで神溺教団に操作されていたなんて
Yes...
はい
You were given orders to steal back a very
important Book from the Acting Director.
あなたは代行から大事な「本」を奪い返すようにと命を受けていた
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
はい　ほかにも何かを聞いていたようにも思うのですが
Yes... I think they asked me
to do other things, as well.
But my memories are still foggy...
今はおぼろげて…
You can't remember?
思い出せませんか？
Milepoc, Renas is tired.
ミレポックさん　レナスさんはお疲れよ
Call it a day.
今日はここまでになさい
Then I have but one final question.
では最後にひとつだけ
Have you ever heard of Lascall Othello?
ラスコール＝オセロについて　知っていることは？
Huh?
え？
Stopping by, Hamy?
お前か　ハミュッ
Milepoc's been digging for info.
ミレポックが嗅ぎ回り出した
I'm sure she'll come asking around soon.
あの調子じゃ　いずれ聞きに来るぞ
Her intuition kicks in at weird times, huh?
変なところで勘が働くのよねえ　あの子も
まぁ　来たら考えるわよ
I'll think about it when she comes.
More importantly, where's the butter knife?
It's not where it used to be.
それよりバターナイフどこ？　場所変えたでしょう
Yeah, my last woman lost it.
I haven't seen it since.
あー　前の女がなくして　それっきりさ
Some luck you have.
相変わらずねぇ
I hope you find a girl who suits you.
見つかるといいわね　あんたに合う女の子
There are plenty of fish in the sea.
世界に女はごまんといるからな
Not as many as you'd think...
なかなかいないもんよ
Partners you find ideal, I mean.
自分が理想とする相手なんて
A dream I had earlier got me thinking...
先夢見てと思ったもの
A dream?
夢？
Yep. I dreamt I was defenseless,
having lost my sling, and was killed.
そう　投石機をなくしてなすすべなく殺される夢
By Mokkania?
モッカニアか？
Colio Tonies.
コリオ＝トニス
あれに殺されるのが理想だったのかもね
Being killed by him might
be the ideal way to die...
Say, Matt?
ねぇ　マット
Hmm?
ん？
If no one out there can kill me,
もし　あたしを殺せる人誰もいなくなったら
マット　殺してくれる？
will you do it, Matt?
You're okay with that?
いいのか？
ふん　やっぱ　いや
Actually, never mind!
That's right. The world is irrational.
そう　世界は理不尽だ　あの時から
Ever since then, that's been the only constant.
それだけは変わっちゃいない
Todomaru mono oroka narishi
止まる者　愚かなりし
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
Harari hirari yubi ni fureta
kuroi tsubasa no hitohira
诸
神&动漫国
君が一つの　物語なら
Kimi ga hitotsu no monogatari nara
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
Mada ikura demo kakikaerareru
血のインクは乾かない
Chi no inku wa kawakanai
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
Dare mo shiranai hontou no bokura
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
Areta sekai kaeru no wa
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
Oimotometa no wa
Chippoke na koufuku nanka ja nai
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Tatakae todoroku kodou wo aizu ni
意のまま　進めば
Inomama susumeba yukusaki hatenai
行く先　果てない
抗え　のたうち
Aragae notauchi ikudo to yaburedo
幾度と　汚れと
Kizamou matotta kizuato ni yume wo
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
Umoresou na kyo no kioku
tsunageru tame ni ashita e
Episode 12
The Past, Irrationality, and a Pipe's Smoke
第12话 过去
与
无理
和
烟斗之烟
Gamo!
ガモ！
Hey! See this?
でさ　これがさ　タバコと味が違うんだぜ
It tastes different from cigarettes.
Really?
本当？
It smells kind of bitter.
なんか渋いにおい
Geez...
いたーなぁ
Who are you kidding?
なーに　しゃれてんだよ
That's something an old man who already
figured this world out would smoke.
そういうのは
世の中を分かったつもりになってる爺が通用なもんだろうな
Matt! Lillian was in tears!
ちょっと　マット　リリヤ泣いてたわよ
バロリー家の屋敷見せてやるて言われたからついてたのに
You said to her you'd show her the Balory
Mansion and then stuck her with the bill!
食い逃げされたって
You're still doing that?
お前　まだそういうことをやってるのか
Nothing gets the ladies
like lineage and status.
女を引っ掛けるには家柄と地位が一番だ
That goes for you, too.
お前もそうだったよな
What are you talking about? l-
なによ　それ　わたしを…
Hey! Get off me!
ちょっと　止せよ
Oh, I get it. You're jealous.
分かってるって　妬いてるんだろう
Jealous, my ass!
What're you talking about?!
妬いてるんなんかじゃないわ　なに言ってるの
Mattalast.
マットアラスト
ああ　お婆ちゃん
Ma'am!
I let the police know there's
an illegal pub here.
不法営業の酒場があると連絡しておきました
They'll arrive in ten minutes.
あと10分で保安官たちが駆けつけます
I stopped time around your ankles.
足のまわりだけ時間を止めました
Seems you're looking to never
make it past trainee, Gamo.
どうやら訓練生で終わりたいようですね　ガモ
No, I was just...
いいえ　これは…
Can I get you something?
ご注文は？
How about some blood from your nose?!
あなたの鼻血でも　いただきましょうか
As you requested.
お待たせしました
I can't believe you blew off a job personally
ordered by the Acting Director.
代行直々の仕事をすっぽかしておくなんて
Fotona was not pleased.
フォトナさん　怒っていたわよ
That's just swell.
そりゃよかった
I don't like him.
俺はあの人のこと嫌いなんて
A child prodigy who was promoted to Librarian
at fifteen would say that, wouldn't he?
さすが15で司書に昇進した天才児　言うことが違うわねぇ
Thank you.
そりゃどうも
What will it take to satisfy you?
何が不満なの？
Everything, I guess.
全部ですかね
Armed Librarians are the defenders
of the world's Books and its peace.
武装司書はあらゆる「本」と世界の平和の守護者よ
It's not a job anyone can get.
望んでもだれもなれるものじゃない
Your point?
だから？
Screw that precious world of yours.
その大事な世界ってやつがさ　くだらないんですよ
The world has nothing but
irrationality and dissatisfaction.
世界には理不尽と不満しかない
What's the point of defending it?
そんな世界を救ってなになるんです？
What's so funny?
何がおかしい？
だいてい　武装司書だってなりたくてなったわけじゃない
I didn't become an Armed Librarian
because I wanted to!
You guys were just overly
obsessed with my talent!
あんたらが俺の才能に惚れ込んだから…
Try clinging to that and don't let go, okay?
せいぜいそこにしがみ付いて生きていくことね
Damn you!
止めとく
Enough!
Your eardrums will get smashed again!
また鼓膜破られるぞ
Damn!
What a rack.
でかいな
Huh?
あ？
I just fell in love at first sight
with that country girl.
田舎娘に一目ぼれってね
Are you serious?
まじかよ
I'm going home.
俺は帰るからな
What have you got there?
それなに？
A friend. A friend who's
probably this world's savior.
友だち　友だちでたぶん世界の救世主
That's pretty lame.
それは…くだらないね
Agreed. I hate it, too.
そうね　わたしも大嫌い
でも友達はこいつだけだから
But it's my only friend.
Then can I be your second one?
じゃ　俺が二人目か？
You've got nice skin.
いい鼻
That's the first time a girl's said that to me.
初めてだな　そこを褒めてくれて女は
That might be the police.
保安官な　これ
名前は？
What's your name?
Hamyuts. Hamyuts Meseta.
ハミュッツ　ハミュッツ＝メセタ
What's yours?
あんなは？
Mattalast Balory, Armed Librarian.
マットアラスト＝バロリー　武装司書
ふんー　あんた　強い？
Are you strong?
Uh, I just told you I'm an Armed Librarian.
武装司書って聞こえなかったな？
So? Are you stronger than me?
そんなこと　どうでもいい
あたしより　強い？
Care to find-
試してみ…
I knew it!
本当だ
Chacoly's a big fat liar.
やっぱりチャコリンは嘘ばっかりだ
There is someone stronger than me.
あたしより強い人いるじゃない？
I thought you were just a seamstress.
ただの針っ子かと思っていたね
Looks like I made a good friend, though.
どうやらいい友達になれそうだ
Friend? Stop that now.
友だち？　やめようよ
わたしが本気であんたのこと好きになったら　この世界は滅ぶから
If I end up truly liking you,
the world will be destroyed.
Huh?
ああ？
殺し合うほうがいい
We should fight to the death.
If you kill me,
あたしのこと殺したら　世界は救えるよ
the world might be saved.
Maybe we'd be better off as friends, then.
じゃ　友達のほうがいいか？
I was right.
正確だ　避けてなきゃ二秒後には…
She needs to dodge in two seconds.
Having to use this...
こいつを使わせるかも
She's strong.
強い　こいつ　とんでもなく強いぞ
Unbelievably strong!
She's going to miss!
外す
Amazing! You're amazing!
すごい　こいつはすごいぞ
あたしは　あんたみたいな人を待っていたのかもしれない
I think you're the man
I've been waiting for.
Huh?
It's okay. You want to
screw me, don't you?
いいよ　したいんでしょう
You're not a virgin?
バージンじゃないのかよ
I wish I could go back and
feel that pain again.
できたら戻りたいな
あの痛さ　最高だから
Nothing can top it...
So you're into that stuff?
そういうのが趣味か？
What stuff?
そういうの…
She doesn't seem like your type.
お前のタイプではなさそうだな
But isn't she a fun girl, Vizak?
でもなかなか面白いですよ　ビザクさん
What? So there are little kids here, too.
うん　こんな小さな子もいるんだ
I-I'm not a kid.
こ、子ともじゃないんです
やめてください
Please stop that!
Volken, infatuation with women
will only lead to your demise.
ヴォルケン
女に現を抜かしていると身を滅ぼすぞ
I'm not... I'm...
そんなこと　僕は…
お嬢　訓練生のルイクだ　お手合わせ願おう
Young lady.
This is a trainee, Ruweek.
You two will spar.
Nice to meet you.
宜しく
Begin!
始め！
ねぇ
See?
Are you plotting something?
何か企んでいるのか？
World destruction, maybe?
世界の破滅かな
If Vizak is willing to vouch
for her aptitude,
ビザクの評価がこれだけ高いのであれば
訓練生として認めてもいいだろう
I'll permit her to undergo training.
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
He's the top person in charge?
あれが一番偉い人？
まぁな　フォトナ館長代行さまだ
Yeah. He's the revered
Acting Director Fotona.
But he looks so weak.
あんなに弱そうなのに？
やっぱりお前には分かるか
You can tell, huh?
He's stronger than that old man,
さっきのお爺さんよりは強いけど
but give me a month and I could beat him.
一ヶ月もあれば倒せるかな
And the old lady?
お婆ちゃんは？
Three months.
三か月
I'll pass you in six months, too.
マットも半年あれば追いぬけるよね
Me?
俺？
That's about right for you,
wouldn't you say?
そのぐらいでしょう　マットって
Stay still.
じっとしてなさい
You'll learn to be more careful,
no matter what,
これ以上大事な肌を傷つけたくなかったら
if you don't want to damage
your precious skin.
金輪際　無茶はしないことね
I'm being careful!
無茶なんかしてないわよ
あっ　いた
Ow!
That hurts, ma'am.
お婆ちゃん　痛い
Take a reality check!
自覚を持ちなさい
No one's ever made it to
1st-rank in four years before.
４年で１級なんで前代未聞
All eyes are on you now.
なたは注目を浴びってるのよ
Yes, yes.
はいはい
Got cut up good again, huh?
また派手に切られたな
She's still getting dressed.
まだ着替え中だよ
Who cares about that?
いいよ　そんなの
それで　向こうの兵力はどのぐらい残ってるんです？
So? How many soldiers
of theirs survived?
None.
全滅よ
Huh?
あ？
The target had already escaped,
目標が逃亡したあとだから　撤退していいって言ってるのに
so we told her she could withdraw.
Pulling out is no fun.
だって　つまらないんだもん
Ireia took these photographs.
イレイアが撮ってきた
正真正銘全滅だ
Slaughtered, every last one of them.
The level to which she goes above
the call of duty is unparalleled.
任務に就かせてから信じられないレベルで成果をあげてきている
That's fantastic. It makes our lives easy.
いいことじゃないですか　俺たちが楽できる
Stop with the jokes.
冗談はよせ
Likewise, can you stop pretending
to be righteous, Acting Director?
代行も　その正義感ぶった顔をやめてもらえませんかね
She needed a year to move beyond apprentice,
見習いこそ一年を用したが
but she hit 3rd-rank in two years,
その後　二年で三級　四年で一級
and 1st-rank in four.
Rather than call it "able," I'd say "peculiar."
有能というより　異常と言ったほうがいい
一般人から見れば　ここにいるのは誰だって異常の変体ばかりだ
To normal people, everyone here
looks peculiar and weird.
She's dangerous.
あの女は危険だ
If we do not act, she will
pose a threat to us-
放っておけば我々に
いや　世界の脅威となる
No, to the world.
You've heard of the traitor, Hiza, yes?
裏切り者ハイザは知っているな
お婆ちゃんから聞きました
Ireia told me. He escaped
by the skin of his teeth.
間一髪で取り逃がしたぞ
We cannot openly act against Imperial forces.
帝国軍と面だって　対立するわけにはいかない
I want you and Hamyuts to take care of him.
今度はお前とハミュッツで処分してもいい
Make it clean.
手際がよくな
なるほど
I see. That is how you would think.
あんたらしい考え方だな
In the process, eliminate Hamyuts as well.
同時に　ハミュッツも消せ
You're obsessed with her. I can tell.
ますますらしい　惚れこです
Mattalast.
マットアラスト
あの女をここに誘ったのは貴様だったな
You're the one who invited her
into our ranks, correct?
She has breasts to die for.
いい胸してたんで
あの女は最初からここに来ようとして　お前に誘わせたのではないか
Are you sure her goal wasn't
to come here all along?
And that she didn't con
you into inviting her?
What are we talking about? Love?
恋の話ですか？
I'm talking about the world.
この世界の話だ
Huh?
Bring her with you to the
second sealed library.
一緒に　第二封印書庫まで来い
Welcome back!
お帰り
ただいま
Hello.
Guess what I made for dinner.
ディナー　何だと思う？
うん　コロッケト
Croquettes.
はずれ　ヒント　におい
Nope. Its smell is the hint.
ステーキか
Steak?
No! It's red.
違うわよ　赤
Tomatoes?
トマト
You aren't even trying!
あんまり考えてないんでしょう
I learned the truth about this world.
世界の真実　聞いてきた
Yeah? How does that make you feel?
そう　感想は？
It's just as I thought.
The world is pointless and irrational.
俺の思ったとおり　どこまでもくだらなくて　理不尽だった
That's great! Your prediction
was right on the money.
よかったじゃない　予想が当って
Sex, now.
するぞ
Hey! Dinner's gonna get cold!
な、なによ　食事冷めちゃう
We'll eat after we finish.
後で食べる
Geez... If you insist...
もう　しょうがないな
But make me feel so good
I think I'm gonna die.
じゃ　死ぬほど気持ちよくして
Of course.
もちろんだ
You haven't made me feel
like I'm gonna die lately.
最近　死ぬほどじゃない
When girls die, having never told the
person they love their feelings,
恋する少女が思いを伝えられず　命を落としたとき
he delivers their Book to their beloved.
その「本」を思い人へと届けてあげるのです
Huh? I didn't know you had a pipe.
あれ　そんなもの持ってるんだ
It was my grandfather's keepsake.
爺さんの形見だ
家に金がなくなっても　これにだけはしがみ付いてた
Even when he lost every penny he had,
he never let go of this.
Such ridiculous pride...
I feel bad for him.
くそみたいなプライドだ
可哀そうな爺さんだったよ
Oh...
ふーん　そっくりだったんだ　マットに
That sounds just like you, Matt.
Hey.
なぁ
Hmm?
うん？
What would you do if I said
I'm going to kill you?
お前のこと　殺すって言ったらどうする？
You're the only person by whose
hands I don't want to die.
あたしね　マットにだけは殺されたくないの
The only one...
それだけは　いやなの
He's here. Hiza...
いる　ハイザよ
Just where the old lady said.
How should we do it?
お婆ちゃんの言ったとおりか
どうする？
You stay here.
マットはここにいてよ　あたし一人でやって来ちゃうから
I'll kill him myself.
You're serious?
本気か？
They've got an entire battalion
of thousands in the forest.
森の中には一個師団　砲台は全て森の中を狙ってる
They've got all their eyes on the woods,
and their guard is flawless.
守りも完璧
二秒後の予知能力と銃だけじゃ…ねぇ
All you have is your ability to see two
seconds into the future and your gun.
Right?
This is gonna be fun.
楽しい
See ya!
じゃねえ
Hamy.
ハミュッ
Huh?
ああ？
I'm gonna take a nap.
寝てるぞ
Knock yourself out.
ご自由に
She's dangerous.
あの女は危険だ
If we do not act, she will
pose a threat to us-
放っておけば確実に我々…
No, to the world.
いや　世界の脅威となる　手に負えない存在と…
She'll be beyond our reach.
What a load of bull...
うまいこと言うね
Hamy!
ハミュッ
This is awesome! I'm having a blast.
楽しい　これ楽しい
Are you all right?
大丈夫か？
あばら二三本　出ちゃったかも
I broke two or three ribs.
I just about had an orgasm.
Go rest. I'll head in.
休んで　俺が行く
Nope.
無理よ　マットには無理
You can't handle this.
Wait!
Come back, Hamyuts!
ハミュッツ　戻れ　ハミュッツ
Hamyuts!
Oh...
That sounds just like you, Matt.
ふーん　そっくりだったんだ　マットに
Tank unit prepared to depart.
われわれ戦車隊はこれより出撃する
All soldiers, get ready!
総員　準備
Found ya.
みーつけた
That's her! Hurry!
あれです　早く
Understood. Ready the cannon!
分かっている　砲撃用意
Wha-?!
Impossible. Tanks!
馬鹿な　戦車隊
Hurry! Now!
次　早く
Yeah, I love it when it heats up.
かえて　熱くなるのが楽しみだね
This was... Hamyuts's doing.
これは　ハミュッツ
あたし　あんたみたいな人を待っていたのかもしれない
I think you're the man I've been waiting for.
That's about right for you, wouldn't you say?
それぐらいでしょう　マットって
You're the only person by whose
hands I don't want to die.
あたしね　マットにだけは殺されたくないの
We should fight to the death.
殺し合うほうがいい
If you kill me,
あたしのこと殺したら　世界は救えるよ
the world might be saved.
Are you sure her goal wasn't
to come here all along?
あの女は最初からここに来ようとして　お前に誘わせたのではないか
And that she didn't con
you into inviting her?
The end already?
もう　おしまいか
Are you gonna kill me?
殺す？
You're the only person by whose
hands I don't want to die.
わたし　マットだけには殺されたくないなぁ
For whatever reason,
no matter where you go,
どうやら　どこまで行ってもこの世界は理不尽らしい
the world is irrational.
Ugh. I think I used too
many coffee grounds.
いやだ　豆の量間違えたかしら
Hey.
ねえ　いつからだっけ　パイプ
Huh?
When'd you start smoking a pipe?
さぁ　いつだったかな
You know, I don't remember.
Taiyo tojiru mae ni
Hikari wo nakushite
Mekurumeku arashi nara
Temaneku mae ni tobikomu
Dare mo itsuka owaru no deshou
Sono hi ga kureba
Mawaridasu mirai wo mezashite
Tada sore wa mou shirusarete ita to shitemo
Sagashidasu kizutsuku imi sae kono te ni
Jibunrashiku aru tame ni
A Day Off,
Connected by a God's stone sword:
神の石剣が結びつけた
two beautiful tales.
二つの可憐な物語
A Day Off, a Picture Book,
two beautiful tales.
The bell sounds far and wide,
signaling the show's start.
鳴り響く開映ので
A Day Off, a Picture Book, and Rusty Hair
The bell sounds far and wide,
signaling the show's start.
休假与画册和锈红色之发
A Day Off, a Picture Book, and Rusty Hair
When the curtain rises,
幕があげが　そこは
there sits a drenched street corner.
濡れそぼった街角